Guide to the Charles Gilbert Hine Photograph Collection 1883-1908 PR 82
New-York Historical Society
Charles Gilbert Hine Photograph Collection
1883-1908
New-York Historical Society
PR 82
9.92 Linear feet (10 boxes)
Platinum, cyanotype, and albumen prints of various Manhattan locations dating from 1883-1908. Views of streets, buildings, businesses, monuments, theaters, billboards, posters, celebrations, and scenes of everyday life are included. The collection also contains a three volume set of photograph albums which portrays Broadway from north to south and includes historical essays and clippings.
Provenance
Gift of Charles Gilbert Hine in 1910, 1917, and 1922.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 20 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Biographical Note
Charles Gilbert Hine was an accomplished insurance publisher, editor, local historian and amateur photographer. Born in 1859 in New Albany, Indiana, he moved with his family to the New York area in 1868 where Hine's father, Charles Cole Hine, became owner and editor of the Insurance Monitor. Hine spent most of his youth living in Woodside, New Jersey, a rural suburb of Newark. The family had a love of sailing and spent summers at their house on Martha's Vineyard, Massachusetts.
Hine and his brothers, Thomas and Edward Hine, learned photography from their father at an early age; their house on Martha's Vineyard had been specifically designed to include a darkroom. Charles and Thomas Hine used their skills to write and privately publish their first book in 1883, Chronicles of Our White Mountain Trip, July 1883, which was heavily illustrated with the brothers' photographs. In 1888 the Hine brothers and their father became founding members of the Newark Camera Club. Charles and Thomas Hine exhibited 157 photographs in the club's First Annual Exhibit in 1891.
Charles Hine and his two brothers joined their father in the family business, the Hine Insurance Publishing Company. After Charles Cole Hine's death in 1897, the brothers incorporated the company. Charles Gilbert Hine succeeded his father as head of the company, editor of the Insurance Monitor, and head of the Underwriters & Credit Bureau, Inc.
Hine pursued his interest in local history throughout the rest of his life. He traveled primarily by foot and bicycle, taking photographs and collecting historical anecdotes. He focused his work on New York and New Jersey, especially along the Hudson River and on Staten Island where he lived for six years. Hine continued to travel to and document the history of Martha's Vineyard where he had spent his childhood summers. He published much of his historical work and accompanying photography in a limited edition series under the title Hine's Annuals between 1905 and 1915. He published historical books and pamphlets separately as well; his dated works span the years from 1883 to 1928. Like other Pictorialist photographers of his era, Charles Gilbert Hine favored the platinum print, known for its delicate gradation of grays and its varied tonal scale. The majority of his published histories included his platinum prints. His accompanying writings are opinionated and express a deep appreciation for the natural landscape and historical architecture portrayed in his photographs. Hine made particular efforts to photograph buildings that were threatened with demolition. He took a special interest in historic thoroughfares; among his published writings were histories of Broadway, the Albany Post Road, Old King's Highway, and the Serpentine Road on Staten Island.
Hine moved to Staten Island with his brother Thomas in 1909. There he served as a member of both the Staten Island Antiquarian Society and the Staten Island Historical Society. In 1915 Hine married his first cousin Sarah Tilden. They immediately moved from Staten Island to East Orange, New Jersey, where he resided until his death in 1931.
Scope and Content Note
The Charles Gilbert Hine Photograph Collection spans the period from 1883 to 1908 and contains platinum prints, cyanotypes, albumen prints, silver prints, and a series of three photograph albums containing an historical essay and clippings which document Manhattan at the turn of the 20th century. The collection is divided into two series: Photographic Prints and Photograph Albums. The collection contains views of streets, buildings, businesses, monuments, major events, and scenes of everyday life in Manhattan.
Arrangement
Materials have been arranged into two series based on format:
Missing Title
Series I: Photographic Prints
Series II: Photograph Albums
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Additional views of Manhattan by other photographers and publishers can be found in the Geographic File (PR 020), the Postcard File (PR 054), and the Stereograph File (PR 065). The New-York Historical Society Library owns several of Charles Gilbert Hine's privately published local history books which feature his photographs. For further information on Hine, see the Charles Gilbert Hine Papers at the Staten Island Historical Society.
Photographic prints.; Broadway (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Advertising -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works.; Billboards -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works.; Streets -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works.; Photograph albums.; Theaters -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works.; Broadway (New York, N.Y.) -- History; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Pictorial works.; Albumen prints.; Cyanotypes; Clippings (information artifacts); Platinum prints.; Hine, Thomas Avery
- Series I: Photographic Prints
  Scope and Contents note
  consists of 161 platinum prints, 21 cyanotypes, and 5 albumen prints dating from approximately 1883 to 1908. The photographic prints in this series were originally integrated into the Geographic File (PR 020); they were removed to create the Charles Gilbert Hine photograph collection. Photographs in this series are arranged numerically; an index listing streets, prominent locations, and subjects can be found at the end of the finding aid. The first forty-one prints have been matted (with the exception of number 026), thereafter they have been placed in folders in groups of approximately ten. The albumen prints in this series are labeled as being taken by both Charles Gilbert Hine and Thomas A. Hine. Titles correspond to the descriptions Hine wrote on the verso of his photographs or on their backings. Titles in brackets have been supplied in cases where the photograph was removed from its original backing. A set of copy prints of Hine photographs used in the exhibition Charles Gilbert Hine: Impressions of a City, held at the New-York Historical Society from October 1990 through January 1991, have been labeled with photograph numbers and can be found after the index.
  Photographs in this series portray a variety of street scenes, buildings, and scenes of daily life in New York that demonstrate Hine's keen eye for lighting and composition. Side streets and main thoroughfares are shown from a variety of vantage points. Street vendors, theater and product advertisements, night views of Madison Square Theatre, and a variety of views of Washington Square Park are only a few of the subjects represented. A few rooftop views are included in the collection. Some photographs show street decorations for the Columbian Celebration in 1892 and the centennial celebration of George Washington's presidential inauguration in 1889. Historical landmarks such as the Jumel Mansion, City Hall, and Hamilton Grange with its thirteen trees are pictured, as is the demolition of the pre-Revolutionary Rhinelander Sugar House Prison.
  - Fifth Avenue, north from 42nd Street, [1903] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Broad Street, south of Wall Street, [1900] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - 201 West 10th Street, [1900] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fulton Street, east from west of Water Street, [1905] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Reade Street [west of Centre Street] (cyanotype), [1895] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Madison Square Theatre [night view], [1905] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - [Future site of West Broadway, tunnel between Vesey and Barclay Streets], [1890] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Liberty Street at William, 1892 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fifth Avenue, looking south [from 53rd Street], [1900] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ruins [Rhinelander] Sugar House Prison, [1900] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 010a)
  - Ruins [Rhinelander] Sugar House Prison, [1900] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 010b)
  - Grove Street and Greenwich Park, east from West 4th Street, [1900] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - [Pushcarts in the park], [1900] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
  - [Washington Square Arch], [1905] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
  - Centre Street [snowstorm], [1905] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
  - [Watts Street at Hudson Street], [1899] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
  - Rear of 112 Ninth Avenue, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
  - South side Washington Square, looking west, 1894 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
  - [Wall Street, corner of Nassau Street], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  - Riverside Drive, at west 106th Street, [1900] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
  - [Worth Street, north side, west of Baxter Street], [1894] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  - Wood arch, Washington Square, 1889 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  - Old doorway, West 17th Street [corner of Eighth Avenue], [1900] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
  - [Hamilton Grange], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
  - Fire at 64-66 Nassau Street (cyanotype), 1898 Feb. (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
  - Thirteen trees and Alexander H. House [Hamilton Grange], undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 25)
  - [University Building, Washington Square East], 1894 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 26)
  - [Riverside Park, between West 125th and 127th Streets], [1905] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 27)
  - [150th Street, towards Seventh Avenue], [1895] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 28)
  - [Battery Park, man reading paper], [1900] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 29)
  - A busy day on West Street, [1900] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 30)
  - [Upper Manhattan Bridge], [1905] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 31)
  - [South Street], [1902] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 32)
  - Southeast corner or Washington Square [looking south on Wooster Street], [1902] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
  - [West Street, north of Cortlandt Street], 1892 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34)
  - [Poster advertising "Mrs. Langtry and her company"], [1900] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 35)
  - [Pushcart in front of wall of posters], [1900] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 36)
  - The children's corner [West Street], [1900] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 037a)
  - [Billboards], undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 037b)
  - [Poster advertising California Fruit chewing gum and "The Devil's Deputy"], [1905] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
  - [Poster advertising Figaro Licorice Sticks], 1894 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 039a)
  - [Poster advertising Old Hoss Bill Hoey in "The Flams"], 1894 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 039b)
  - [Posters advertising Sherman Park and Hecker's Buckwheat], 1894 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 40)
  - [Café entrance], [1905] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 41)
  - [Hamilton Grange], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 42)
  - [Bleecker Street], [1902] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 43)
  - Broadway, at corner of Morris Street (cyanotype), [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 44)
  - St. Paul's [Broadway, looking south] (duplicate prints), [1889] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 045-046)
  - Steamship's Row, lower end Broadway (cyanotype), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 47)
  - [Canal Street], [1901] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 48)
  - [Chambers Street, south side], [1900-1905] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 49)
  - [Chambers Street, south side and Pearl Street (cyanotype), [1885-1890] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 50)
  - Cortlandt Street, 4-10 Cortlandt Street, [1892] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 51)
  - [Duane and Centre Street] (cyanotype), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 52)
  - Greenwich Avenue [south from Jane Street], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 53)
  - [Maiden Lane], [1896] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 54)
  - [Maiden Lane and Liberty Street], 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 55)
  - Maiden Lane, south side from Liberty Street, [1906] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 56)
  - [Nassau Street] (cyanotype), [1893] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 57)
  - [Broad Street and Nassau Street], 1899 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 58)
  - State Street, (8,7,6) facing the Battery, [1898] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 59)
  - [Vandam Street], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 60)
  - Vesey Street [northwest corner at Greenwich Street], [1898] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 61)
  - Vestry Street, north side, 1899 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 62)
  - Washington Street and Christopher Street, 1899 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 63)
  - Old house on Washington Place, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 64)
  - North from southeast on Park Place, 1904 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 065a)
  - North from southeast on Park Place, Steam Engine on Elevated train #2, 1894 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 065b)
  - Tombs, Centre Street, N.Y. (cyanotype), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 66)
  - Home Life Insurance Co. Building, 255-7 Broadway, 1893-1894 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 67)
  - [Bowling Green], [1895] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 68)
  - Broad Street [Fraunces Tavern], [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 069a)
  - [Fraunces Tavern] (cyanotype), [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 069b)
  - Chambers (Mulberry bend) park, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 70)
  - Broadway and 35th Street, night scene, Herald Building, [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 71)
  - [Wall Street, north side and east of Nassau], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 72)
  - Wall Street, [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 73)
  - Wall Street, [1897] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 74)
  - West 4th Street, where it joins Washington Place, [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 75)
  - 123 Washington Place, 1908 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 76)
  - 135 Washington Place, 1900 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 77)
  - [Washington Square North], [1894] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 78)
  - Washington Square South, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 79)
  - Washington Square (cyanotype), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 080a)
  - Washington Square (cyanotype), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 080b)
  - Washington Mews, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 81)
  - Southeast corner of Washington Square (cyanotype), [1902] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 82)
  - Washington Square Arch, [1905] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 83)
  - [Battery Park], [1890] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 84)
  - [Battery Park] (cyanotype), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 85)
  - Riverside Park, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 86)
  - [City Hall Park], [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 87)
  - Vesey Street, 1892 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 88)
  - [City Hall Park] (cyanotype), 1895 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 89)
  - City Hall Park, [1895] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 90)
  - St. Paul's churchyard, [1890-1895] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 91)
  - St. Paul's, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 92)
  - St. Paul's, looking west from alongside south wall of chapel, [1895] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 93)
  - St. Paul's churchyard, [1899] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 94)
  - [Poster advertising John L. Sullivan], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 95)
  - St. Paul's churchyard, [1890-1899] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 96)
  - St. Paul's [chapel], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 97)
  - Trinity Churchyard looking north to Martyrs' Monument and Trinity Building (cyanotype), [1895] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 98)
  - Trinity Churchyard (cyanotype), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 99)
  - St. Patrick's Cathedral, Fifth Avenue, [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 100)
  - West Building at Episcopal Seminary Grounds, Chelsea Square, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 101)
  - Asbury Church and the Benedict - Washington Square, 1894 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 102)
  - [Broadway, including Grace Church], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 103)
  - [Billboards advertising Scott's Emulsion of Pure Cod Liver Oil and Madison Square Theatre], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 104a)
  - [Billboards advertising Scott's Emulsion of Pure Cod Liver Oil and Madison Square Theatre] (silver print), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 104b)
  - [Poster advertising Herrmann], 1894 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 105a)
  - [Billboard advertising Buffalo Bill's Wild West], 1894 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 105b)
  - [Poster advertising "A Fatted Calf"], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 106)
  - Where Laight Street joins Canal, [1902?] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 107)
  - [Posters and clipping on "Business Competition"], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 108)
  - [Billboard advertising women's clothing], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 109)
  - [Poster with little cooking boy], 1895 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 110a)
  - [Posters advertising "Charley's Aunt" and Huber's Museum], 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 110b)
  - [Posters advertising "A Gaiety Girl"], [1894] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 111a-b)
  - [Posters advertising Huber's 14th Street Museum], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 112)
  - [Posters advertising Carpenter Shop and several shows], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 113a)
  - [Two men and a boy at the docks], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 113b)
  - [Poster advertising Barnum & Bailey Greatest Show on Earth], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 114)
  - [Poster advertising the Lillian Russel Opera Comique Co.], 1894 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 115a)
  - [Billboards advertising "The Cotton King," Kendal, etc.], 1895 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 115b)
  - [Billboards advertising Kate Claxton in "The Two Orphans"], 1894 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 116a-b)
  - [Posters advertising Pettijohn's California Breakfast Food and Bidwell-Tinkham Cycle Company], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 117)
  - [Billboards advertising "Too Much Johnson" and "The Gaiety Girls"], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 118a)
  - [Billboards advertising Buffalo Bill's Wild West], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 118b)
  - [Billboard advertising "The Amazons"], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 119a)
  - [Billboard advertising trained animals], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 119b)
  - Old Herald Building, Broadway and Ann Street, [1895] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 120)
  - [Billboard advertising Miss Olga Nethersole], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 121a)
  - [Billboards advertising Buffalo Bill's Wild West, "Rosedale," and Herrmann], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 121b)
  - [Billboard advertising "A Temperance Town," Bob Fitzsimmons, "The Century Magazine", and Orange Athletic Club v. Princeton football game (possibly in Newark, New Jersey)], 1894 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 122a)
  - [Sunset on water with ships in the distance] (cyanotype), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 123)
  - [Ships in dock], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 124)
  - N.Y. skyline [ship in foreground], [1888] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 125)
  - [Harlem River], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 126)
  - Cloud Study (cyanotype), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 127)
  - Fifth Avenue Hotel, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 128)
  - Bird's Eye View, northwest from 100 William Street, [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 129)
  - Between Broadway and Nassau Street, north of and from Wall Street, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 130)
  - Broadway in 1885 form a window of 168 Broadway. The turn in the curb on the left is for Cortlandt Street (albumen), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 131)
  - [Bird's eye view, Broadway and Water Street], [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 132)
  - East from Equitable Building, United States Hotel (albumen), 1885 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 133)
  - North from Equitable Building, 120 Broadway, W.U. Telegraph Building, Evening Post, Post Office, Tribune (albumen), [1885] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 134)
  - Sun, Tribune, Times (albumen), [1883] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 135)
  - [Washington Heights section, Amsterdam Avenue view north from High Bridge tower], [1904] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 136)
  - South from Equitable Building about 1885. Note telegraph poles on Broadway. (albumen) (Offsite-box 5, Folder 137)
  - [Washington Heights section, view southwest from High Bridge tower, Amsterdam Avenue with 172nd Street in foreground], [1904] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 138)
  - Columbian Celebration, 1892 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 139)
  - Columbian Celebration, 1892 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 140)
  - Columbian Celebration/Temporary Arcade, 1892 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 141)
  - Columbian Celebration, 1892 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 142)
  - When the Washington Building was a building and Trinity's spine had some show, Castle Garden was the headquarters for imported labor [Castle Garden with the Washington Building being constructed in background, Trinity Church to the left], 1883 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 143a)
  - W.U. Telegraph, Trinity, Washington Building, Castle Garden, Produce Exchange, 1883 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 143b)
  - [Bridge receding], undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 144)
  - [Skyline at pier 14] (cyanotype), undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 146)
  - [Castle Garden], 1894 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 147a)
  - [Castle Garden], [1900] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 147b)
  - [Old fort in upper end of Morningside Park], undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 148)
  - [Trees] (cyanotype), undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 149)
  - [Old run-down shack], undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 150)
  - [Shack with broken-down wagon], undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 151a-b)
  - 13 Trees [at Hamilton Grange], undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 152)
  - National Bank of Commerce, 31 Nassau Street, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 153)
  - [Fireplace at Hamilton Grange], undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 154)
  - Jumel Door [Jumel Mansion], undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 155)
  - Alexander Hamilton House [Hamilton Grange], undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 156)
  - [Jumel Mansion], undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 157a)
  - [Jumel Mansion], undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 157b)
  - [Hiram Sammis, tailor, 240 Broadway] (cyanotype), [1893] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 158)
  - [Policeman watching bicycle riders], undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 159)
  - [Three gentlemen standing in front of a wagon], undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 160)
  - "That tired feeling" [man sitting in front of Wine Room], undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 161)
  - [Trolley Station], undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 162a)
  - [Billboard advertising Madame Sans Gene], 1895 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 162b)
  - [Rhinelander] Sugar House Prison, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 163)
  - University Building, Washington Square [detail of sculpture], 1894 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 164)
  - Grant's Tomb, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 165)
  - Fifth Avenue and West 52nd Street, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 166)
- Series II: Photograph Albums
  Series II consists of a series of three photograph albums with an accompanying typewritten text and clippings on the history of various locations along Broadway in Manhattan. Hine has entitled his volumes Broadway, New York From the Sky Scraper to the Wild Flower. The 274 photographs in these volumes are platinum prints with the exception of five cyanotypes. The photographs date from 1885-1908; many are undated. The volumes and the prints within them are arranged geographically, following Broadway from south to north. The volumes have been disbound due to their fragile condition, and the pages have been numbered to retain their original order.